I was posting on my social media and suddenly felt a bit down
刚才发着发着朋友圈突然有点郁闷啊
Why is that?
为什么呢
Because I thought about a deeply rooted issue
因为我想到了一个根深蒂固的问题
That the happiness in life comes from intense self-deception
就是人生的快乐来自于高强度的自我欺骗啊
Many people refuse to draw a clear line with reality
很多人拒绝与现实啊划清界限
always feeling that they should live in an ideal world
总是觉得要活在理想当中
but one day, they will wake up to the reality
可是理想当中他有一天他终于会清醒
and realize that the real world is not what they imagined
他发现现实的世界不是那个样子
leading to disappointment with reality
随即呢对现实感到失望
thinking that the world needs to be saved
觉得要拯救这个世界
but in fact, the world has always been this way
其实这个世界从来就是这个样子
it doesn’t need to be saved
并不需要被拯救啊
it’s just that you need to understand the inherent laws of the world
只是你对这个世界孩子它本身的运行规律呢
Still don't get it
还是不了解啊
Why do you say life is about intense self-deception?
为什么说人生在于高强度的自我欺骗呢
Because when people live in reality
因为人在生活在真实当中的时候
they can't handle it
他会受不了啊
the true state of human beings
人真实的情况
is often something they can't perceive like the fall of Miss Dong do you really think the fall of Miss Dong means better days are ahead?' Actually, that's not the case. But I don't think it's a bad thing.
很多的时候都是自己无法感知到的 就像董小姐的倒下一样 你觉得董小姐的倒下真的就是啊 好日子就来了嘛 其实并不是的 但是我并不觉得这是件坏事
Because you need to realize that.
因为你就要意识到啊
You've read the novel 'Blood Red Romance,' right?
这个血色浪漫这个小说看过吧
Isn't that right?
对不对
And you've seen the early films directed by Feng Xiaogang, haven't you?
冯小刚拍的早年拍的戏也看过吧
So often, the fate of the rich and the poor ends up differently.
所以很多的时候就是那个富贵命跟这个贱命
The ultimate outcomes are different.
最终的结局是不一样的
Even if you have the same skills as Xiao Huang Dan.
你就算有小黄蛋那样的本事
You won’t outdo Zhong Yuemin either.
你也不会干得过钟跃民的
It’s the same principle.
就是一个道理
So no matter what,
所以无论怎么样
you need to understand that
你要明白
everyone’s ultimate outcome is different.
人每个人的这个最终的结局是不一样的啊
So what kind of difference should you create in your life?
所以你应该在你的人生中创造什么样的不一样
This is crucial.
这个很重要
That is to say, life is about intense self-deception,
那也就是说人生在于高强度的自我欺骗的
its fundamental meaning.
根本的意义
It's about giving your own life meaning.
就是你要赋予你自己的生命有意义啊
It's not about the meaning others impose on it.
并不是在于别人说的意义啊
After all, good people don't always get good outcomes.
可能这世界上毕竟就是好人没好报
And bad people don't always face consequences.
恶人没有恶报啊
Things might not always feel fair.
可能没有那么好的感觉
Hard work doesn't always lead to success.
可能有劳未必有所得
Sometimes, the slow and steady don't need to start early. Often, others might have an advantageous position. This can make it hard for you to progress further. Sometimes it's just like that Why does Teacher Dabing say we should cultivate longevity and walk the narrow path?
可能笨鸟不需要先飞 很多的时候就是人家可能占据了很好的位置 你就没有办法继续发展 有的时候就是这样 人为什么大兵老师说要耕寿田走窄门呢
So if you let that stop you
所以你如果你因为这样的话
If you stop putting in the effort
你就不继续努力了
If you give up on moving forward
不继续往下走了
Then your life is over
那你的人生也就结束了啊
So from the moment you feel disappointed
所以从你失望的那一刻开始
You shouldn't be an idealist anymore
你就不应该做一个理想主义者
You should be a realist.
你应该做一个现实主义者
A realist is someone who
现实主义者是这样的
no matter what cards reality deals me,
无论现实给我什么样的牌
no matter what situation I find myself in,
给我什么样的境遇
I play them to the best of my ability.
我都把它打好
I turn the tables and win.
我都把他打成翻身仗
It's that simple.
就是这么简单
No matter what happens,
无论怎么样
I always strive to do better.
我都是往上去争
But no matter what
但是无论怎么样
your outcome might not be truly good
你的结果未必会真的好
but when you accept everything
但是你就接受了这一切的时候
and can still carry on positively
你还能去继续的好的话
then it’s okay
那就OK了
so many things, if you always focus on gains and losses in reality
所以很多的东西如果你永远以现实当中的得失
in reality
现实当中的啊
how to put it
怎么说呢
some feelings that inspire you
一些给你来激励的这种感觉的时候
If you take this as your benchmark your real life will be tough to get through I would say no one has given me the wisdom to survive more than I have given myself
你以这个为这个基准的话 你的现实中就会很难熬啊 可以说我觉得没有谁给我就是生存的智慧 比我自己给自己的更多一点
the meaning of life still lies in convincing yourself
就是人生的意义还是在于你自己要骗自己
you have to tell yourself that these things are meaningful
你自己要说你自己这些东西是有意义的
you have to believe that you are a very fortunate person
你自己要相信自己是一个非常幸运的人
you have to believe in yourself
你要相信自己
this life is definitely meaningful
这一生肯定是有意义的
What would you say for sure?
你肯定是怎么说呢
The chosen one
天选之人
You have to believe in yourself first
你只有自己这么相信了以后
Only then will the heavens truly help you
老天爷才会真的帮你
This is a cause-and-effect relationship
这是一个先后的因果关系
It’s about building something from nothing
就是你自己从无到有
From the false to the true
从假到真
That’s the process
他是这么一个过程
From the start, when no one believed
从最开始没有人相信
Until one or two people believe
到有一两个人相信
Until everyone believes
到所有人都相信
When everyone believes
所有人都相信的时候
It will become true
他就会变成真的了
And there is a cause and effect between things
而且事物之间是有因果的啊
Like the videos I make
你像我做的视频一样
The videos I make and the books I write
做的视频写的书
Now they have helped many people
现在帮助了很多人
But from the perspective of these books and videos
但是从这些书这些视频来讲
Did it come out of nothing?
那是从无就有的吗
How did this process of energy storage come about?
那这个过程这个蓄能这个过程是怎么来的呢
Now it's in a state of emission. I made a video. You saw it. You were inspired. So where do these videos come from? Did they just appear out of thin air? No, they come from all the hardships I've endured.
现在是一个发出的状态 我做了视频 你看到了 你收到了鼓舞 那这些视频是怎么来的呢 是凭空就这么着出来的吗 不是那是所有我吃过的苦
The path we've walked
走过的路啊
The traps we've dug, we find ourselves stuck in
挖过的坑走进去自己出不来
And then we rely on our own efforts to get out
然后自己又靠自己的奋斗出来
So this process
所以这个东西这个过程啊
Everything has a state of accumulating energy and layering up
任何事情都有一个蓄能的一个叠加的一个状态
It's certainly not going to be simple at the very beginning
最一开始的话绝对不会就这么简单
It won't just start off so easily
单单的就这么开始
It definitely takes time
所以一定是慢慢来的
It's gradually achieved
慢慢获得的
So you can't give up just because something doesn't yield immediate results.
所以你不能因为不会一下出结果的事情
You shouldn't completely stop trying.
你就完全不努力了
Things don't change overnight.
不会今天一下就出现改变的事情
You shouldn't undermine today's value just because you don't see immediate change.
你今天就否定了今天的价值
Because the world is shaped by countless days,
因为这个世界就是由无数的今天
by countless individuals.
无数个个人创造出来的啊
And the most important point is,
而最重要的观点就是
you shouldn't rely too much on external feedback.
你不能太去依赖外部世界给你的反馈
Instead, you should rely on the feedback from your own inner world.
而是你要依赖自己内部世界给人的反馈
Feedback from the external world is often delayed.
因为外部世界别人的反馈它通常是迟钝的
This is a symbiotic illusion.
这是一个共生幻象啊
But in your own heart, it's an independent illusion. They are both illusions. Speaking of the consensus illusion outside, It's the world we walk through. The process of interacting with others.
但是你自己的内心里是一个独立的一个幻象啊 同样都是幻象 就是外边这个共识幻象来讲 就是我们走过的世界 你与他人交互的这么一个过程
Receiving encouragement from others in the real world.
在现实世界中得到别人的鼓励
Receiving praise from others.
得到别人的赞美
Getting recognition from others
得到别人的认可
is often a luxury
通常是比较奢侈的
and you have to do a lot to earn it
而你要做很多事情才能得到这些
but if you have a good relationship with your parents
但如果你跟父母的关系好
or if you have very close friends
如果你跟你朋友关系非常好
you might receive these things from them
你可能会从他们手里会得到这些东西
but they also have their own needs
但是他们也是有所求
and expectations
有所需要的
who in this world can provide you with unlimited recognition
这个世界上谁能给你无限制的供给你的认可
Your needs
你的需求
Some psychological cues
你的心理上的一些暗示
Only you can do that
那只有你自己啊
Many people often give themselves so-called motivation
很多人没事老给自己所谓的鞭策
Yourself
自己
So-called
所谓的啊
Don't be afraid of becoming too proud
这个不要怕自己骄傲
It's not about the kind of interaction with parents
他不由父母的那种互动关系来讲
Once you focus on yourself
回到自己身上以后
He is also in a constant state of anxiety.
他也是处于一种恒常的焦虑的状态
A constant anxiety.
恒常的焦虑
A constant sense of dissatisfaction.
恒常的不满足啊
He uses this fear to drive himself.
用于这种恐惧感去驱使自己啊
When he sees the data come in.
看到这个数据下来了啊
When he sees his income decrease. When he realizes his youth is gone. When he sees others surpass him. He feels a sense of crisis. But such things can't last long. Such things can't last long. When in reality you can't quickly
看到自己的收入减少了啊 看到自己青春不在了 看到别人超过了自己 他有一种危机感 但这种东西它是不能长久的 这种东西是不能长久的 当你现实当中没有办法迅速
change your current situation,
改变你这种现状的时候
you'll fall into a greater crisis.
你就会陷入更大的危机
you'll fall into deeper self-doubt.
你就会陷入更大的自我怀疑
This is not the way to go.
这样是不行的
So you need something that, no matter how well or poorly you perform,
所以你需要有一个东西就是无论你干的好与坏
you should encourage yourself.
你都要鼓励自己啊
No matter whether you gain or lose in reality
无论现实当中你是失与得
you should believe in yourself
你都要相信自己的东西
no matter what your personal creed is
无论你的自己的信条是什么啊
for example, many people's creed is to live for themselves
比如说很多人的信条是我就为我自己而活啊
or you can live for the people
或者你可以为人民群众而活
both self-centered and other-centered approaches are valid
都可以为己为他都是可以的
in the end, you'll find that whether you're living for others or for yourself
最终你会发现为他还是为己
it will all come down to the same level
他会回到一个啊一个平面上
it's a process where different paths lead to the same destination
它会有一个殊途同归这么一个过程
So no matter what you think
所以无论你是怎么想的
I just want to live in a big house
我就是想住大房子啊
I just want to make my life better
我就是想让自己生活变得更好
or I just want to improve the lives of the people
或者我就是想让人民的群众的生活变得更好
These are all great things
这些都是很伟大的事情
But these things fall into the realm of idealism
但是这些东西都是理想主义范畴的东西
Idealistic things
理想主义范畴的东西
What kind of inspiration can they offer you? The thing itself is impossible to achieve But the heart can yearn for it. You can pretend it has been achieved. Or you can pretend you have the ability to achieve it.
能够给你一些什么样的启示呢 就是这个东西本身不可能实现 但是呢心可以向往之 你可以假装他实现了 或者你假装你有这种实现的能力
Or you can pretend you are the chosen one.
或者你假装自己是天选自之子之子
It's that simple.
就这么简单
So much of the time, it comes down to the power of faith.
所以很多的时候是在于信仰的加成
Faith itself is like water without a source.
信仰这东西本身就是无根之水
You may never encounter deities in your lifetime.
你一辈子也见不到神仙
Nor will you ever see what God truly looks like.
也见不到上帝到底什么样
You can only wander aimlessly throughout your life.
你一辈子只能在茫茫之中
In the darkness, you blindly believe.
黑暗之中迷迷迷糊糊的就信了啊
All religions tell you,
所有的宗教告诉你
This one tells you,
这个告诉你
That one tells you about various deities,
那个告诉你各种神仙神仙怎么样
What this one is like,
这个怎么样
What that one is like,
那个怎么样
But in reality, you never actually see what these beings truly look like.
但是你其实你都见不到真人什么样
Instead, they create a kind of illusory realm for you.
而是他给你创造的一种虚实的那种幻境
These things can truly inspire you
这些东西真正能够鼓励你
it's the parables within them that do
而是那些他当中的那些寓言故事
the philosophical insights can assist you
那些哲学的道理能够帮助你
it's the teachings of the great masters that stand out
而是他那些立在的那些高僧大德
the knowledge they have uncovered
他们研究出来的这些东西
can truly help you transform your current situation
真正能够帮助你改变你现在的一切啊
or guide you to a better life
或者帮助你走向了更好的生活
whether you adhere to these precepts or not regardless of how you choose to act No matter if it's still you From the philosophical insights of this secular world It's also about reflecting certain things Regardless of how it is Life is about intense self-deception
不管你就遵循这些清规戒律也好 不管你是怎么样做也好 不管还是你自己 从这个世俗当中的这些哲理当中 体现出一些东西也好 无论怎么样 人生都在于高强度的自我欺骗
Faith is a form of deception
信仰就是一种欺骗
The principles you seek in life
你自己找寻的生活当中的道理
Are also a form of deception
也是一种欺骗
This deception is about making the false seem real
这种欺骗就是以假乱真
So, what is actually true?
所以实际上什么东西真正是真的呢
The truth is often hard to define.
真的东西反而是不太好被定义的
Most of it is false.
大部分都是假的
From 0 to 99, it’s all false.
从0~1到99都是假的
It’s only true at 100 percent.
只有百分之百的时候呢
That’s when it’s real.
它是真的
But this 100, this perfect state,
但是这个100呢到百分之百的时候
It becomes one.
他又是一了
So, speaking of truth, it’s a state of perfection.
所以来讲真是一种完美的状态
It's a state of saturation
是一种饱和的一种状态
while most of the false states are imperfect and incomplete
而大部分假一种不完美不残缺的那种状态
that's what makes them real
才是一种真实的状态
meaning that what is false is actually true
也就是说假的东西才是真的
while what is true is only momentary
而真的东西呢只是在一瞬间
the true state is a fleeting moment
真的东西呢是一种瞬间状态
and thus harder to find
反而不容易存在
so you shouldn't pursue the true things
所以你就不应该去追求真的东西
have faith in yourself including all these things including your self-validation these should all be like water without a root so you should never seek others' approval of you others' love for you
信仰自信啊 包括你的这些东西 包括你的自证 这些东西都应该是无根之水 所以你永远不要去寻求别人的对你的认可 别人对你的爱
all sorts of support from others
别人对你的各种各样的支持
you should seek self-approval
你应该寻求自己对自己的这样
because you are the one who empowers yourself
因为自己就是赋能者
you must first empower yourself
你只有先赋能自己
define your own function first
先定义了自己的函数
only then can you truly accomplish everything
你才能真正去完成这一切
so it all starts with yourself
所以这个东西是始于自己啊
narcissists remain invincible by being consistently self-absorbed
自恋者恒常不变得无敌
it's that simple
就是这么简单的道理
so no matter what
所以无论怎么样
don't think that just because you don't have anything real in your hands
不要认为你手里边没有真东西
you can't achieve everything
你就不能去换回这一切了
that's not the case
不是这样的
for all narcissists
所有的自恋狂来讲
they don't need real things to support them
他们都不需要真实的东西去支撑
they can distort reality
他可以扭曲这个现实
you can also refuse to acknowledge this reality
你也可以拒绝认识这个现实
so this is what I want to tell you
所以这个就是我想告诉你的
the meaning of life lies in high-intensity self-deception
人生的意义在于高强度的自我欺骗